Albert Schweitzer Papers
Albert Schweitzer Papers
1896-1965
Schweitzer, Albert, 1875-1965.
18 linear ft.
Papers of the theologian, philosopher, physician, organist, and music scholar; born in Alsace, France. Founded a missionary hospital in Lambaréné, French Equatorial Africa (now Gabon). Received the Nobel Peace Prize in 1952 for his advocacy of the brotherhood of nations. Collection includes correspondence (1901-1965); 123 notebooks (1918-1965); manuscript essays and lectures on religion, philosophy, and medicine; and sermons. Correspondence includes nearly 1400 letters between Schweitzer and wife Hélène Bresslau (1901-1939); 396 letters (1950-1965) written in German to Erica Anderson; 180 letters to daughter Rhena Schweitzer Miller; and 70 letters to various recipients, including 3 to Rudolf Bultmann. Notebooks document Schweitzer's daily life in Lambaréné, the diseases and stories of his patients, and the arrival of visitors to the mission. They also contain poems, quotations, excerpts from books on philosophy, religion, and history; clippings from French, German, English, and African newspapers; reports on world politics; and commentaries on himself and his work.
149738
Biographical History
Albert Schweitzer (January 14, 1875-September 4, 1965), German theologian, philosopher, musician, musicologist, doctor, surgeon, and medical missionary, was born in Kaysersberg, Alsace (French territory then occupied by Germany), the son of a liberal Lutheran minister, Louis Schweitzer, and Adele (Schillinger) Schweitzer. He began music lessons at age five, went on to study theology and philosophy at Strasbourg University and, briefly, philosophy at the Sorbonne in Paris. In 1902 he became a lecturer in the faculty of theology at Strasbourg University, and in the following year principal of the Theological College of St. Thomas.
Even at this young age, Schweitzer was well-known throughout Europe for his achievements in music and theology. He was an exceptional performer and critic of Bach as well as an influential organ-builder whose published works were to change the pattern of organ restoration and installation. In theology and philosophy, his unorthodox ideas about the need for reason and truth within Christian dogma were earning him controversy and praise. The publication in 1906 (1910 in English) of his The Quest of the Historical Jesus, in which Schweitzer took a new look at the Synoptic gospels and tried to understand exactly what Jesus really believed, was a landmark in Christian theology.
In 1896, despite a sucessful scholastic career, Schweitzer decided that he could not live a life purely devoted to academia. "I decided that I would make my life my argument," he said, intending to act out his beliefs rather than just preach them. At the age of thirty he returned to Strasbourg University to study medicine and in 1913 he became a fully qualified doctor, with a specialization in tropical diseases. He began actively to raise funds for the establishment of a hospital in equatorial Africa. Although his unorthodox theology was received by most mission societies with suspicion and disapproval, the Paris Missionary Society at last agreed to sponsor his venture and gave him land on which to build his hospital. This he did, with the help of his wife, Hélène Bresslau, who had qualified as a nurse to help with his mission.
The Schweitzers set up their hospital in Lambaréné, a fiercely tropical area of French equatorial Africa. Schweitzer's unorthodox medical methods (he ran Lambaréné like a typical African village) were frequently criticized but Schweitzer believed that blending African culture with his own techniques would address the needs of the population better than the imposition of a purely Western style upon them. The affection and trust he inspired in those who came to him for treatment and the success of his hospital over the years would seem to confirm this view. The villagers christened him "Oganga," meaning "the fetishman," a term of respect. By the time of his death, Lambaréné had about seventy buildings and attracted dedicated and talented medical staff from around the world.
At the outbreak of World War I he and his wife, both German citizens, were palced under house arrest and eventually taken to an internment camp in France, where they stayed until the end of the war. In 1924 he returned to Lambaréné, rebuilt the hospital on a new site, and spent the rest of his life devoted to its development, traveling regularly to Europe to give concerts to raise funds. Hélène's health suffered after her experience in the internment camp and she remained in Europe, apart from the occasional visit, but their daughter Rhena trained as a laboratory technican so she could work alongside her father.
Prior to the outbreak of World War II, Schweitzer continued to visit and lecture in Germany until the increased power of the Nazis made it no longer safe. The war itself drove Lambaréné to the brink of closure, but assistance from the Unitarian Service Committee in America enabled it to recover.
Schweitzer's ethical system, which he termed Reverence for Life, centered on a belief that everything on earth is equally sacred. "Man's ethics," he said, "must not end with man, but should extend to the universe." In his view, it is up to mankind to invest living with moral value, since nature and the universe are neutral. Schweitzer elaborated this theory in his writings and exemplified it in his own life, refusing to kill anything, even insects, unless it was absolutely essential. (Part of the responsibility of this approach, he knew, was the need to accept that in some situations killing is necessary.)
In 1952 Schweitzer was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize, the money from which he put towards building a leper colony near the hospital. In 1957 Hélène died, and thereafter he remained at Lambaréné. He became increasingly outspoken on the issue of nuclear weapons, joining with some of the greatest intellects in the world to discuss and denounce their proliferation. In 1958 he made three radio appeals from Oslo entitled "Peace or Atomic War?," and until the end of his life he welcomed visiting journalists or politicians who wished to discuss this issue with him.
He died, peacefully, in 1965, and was buried alongside his wife at Lambaréné.
(Biographical statement adapted from World Authors 1900-1950 (1996) Copyright (c) by The H. W. Wilson Company)
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Assembled from a variety of sources, the Albert Schweitzer Papers spans the years 1896 to 1965 and comprises Correspondence, Writings and Memorabilia of the Nobel Peace Prize-winning humanitarian doctor (1875-1965). Of Alsatian background, Schweitzer spoke both French and German, and his notebooks and family correspondence move freely, at times randomly, between the two. In 1913 Albert Schweitzer relinquished a promising career as a theologian and musician to travel to French Equatorial Africa where he established a hospital at Lambaréné on the Ogowe River. Documenting Schweitzer's realization of his own philosophy of "reverence for life," the collection offers an intimate look at the thoughts and daily life of one of the most revered men of the twentieth century.
Arranged alphabetically, the Correspondence/subject files (boxes 1-5) consists primarily of original letters which Schweitzer wrote to his wife Hélène (née Bresslau), his daughter Rhena, and his biographer and friend Erica Anderson. Other correspondents include Emory Ross, Director of the Albert Schweitzer Fellowship, biographer Hermann Hagedorn, and John F. Kennedy, to whom there is a draft of a Schweitzer letter.
Writings (boxes 6-21) includes a working copy with notes for revisions of the book More from the Primeval Forest; essays, including drafts for his three radio messages on the dangers of nuclear proliferation; 127 notebooks covering the years 1918 to 1965; program notes for an organ concert; thoughts on nuclear weapons testing; the script for the documentary film "Albert Schweitzer;" as well as a short story, speeches and sermons.
Constituting the bulk of the Writings and arranged chronologically, the notebooks (boxes 7-19) "make up the core of what might be generally considered Albert Schweitzer's personal journal." (Ursula Berkling "The Albert Schweitzer Papers at Syracuse University", Syracuse University Library Associates Courier, vol.XXI, no.2, Fall 1986, p.27) They embrace a wide variety of topics, including official hospital records and accounts of daily life at Lambaréné, as well as travel diaries of Schweitzer's many concert and/or lecture tours to Europe and the United States. The notebooks also contain observations about people and world events; explorations of ideas in philosophy, theology, linguistics and music; records of and excerpts from Schweitzer's correspondence; financial and personnel records; construction hints; poems; recipes; and many other items indicating a mind that seems to have been interested in everything. Together with the dates and Schweitzer-provided titles for most notebooks, a partial description of their contents is listed.
A watercolor painting by Lambaréné nurse Gloria Coolidge; clippings; photographs, some signed by either Schweitzer or photographer Erica Anderson; a book on harmony and a pamphlet about French missionary work in Africa, both inscribed by Albert Schweitzer to his daughter; two copies of an autograph typescript essay, "Les Deux Frères," by Nikos Kazantzakis; and some early documents from Schweitzer's days as a student at the University of Strassburg constitute Memorabilia (box 22 and oversize package 1). Also included is a mahogany box, possibly made at Lambaréné, which is inscribed "avec mes bonnes pensées Albert Schweitzer."
Original Schweitzer letters to Raymond P. Currier, Hermann Hagedorn, and Emory Ross were relocated to this collection from the Albert Schweitzer Fellowship Records, as were original Schweitzer letters to Clarence F. Avery from the Albert Schweitzer Center Records.
Related Material
The library also holds the Albert Schweitzer Fellowship Records (one series of which is the Albert Schweitzer Center Records). Other Albert Schweitzer-related material at may be found among the papers of Rudolf Bultmann, Edwin T. Dahlberg, Hermann Hagedorn, and Charles R. Joy. See also the
Johanna Reitzer Collection on Albert Schweitzer
.
Subject and Genre Headings
Music; Religion and Philosophy; Science and medicine; Activism and social reform; Anderson, Erica.; Bresslau, Helene, 1879-1957.; Bultmann, Rudolf Karl, 1884-1976.; Schweitzer, Albert, 1875-1965.; Schweitzer Miller, Rhena.; Humanists.; Missionaries, Medical.; Missions -- Gabon.; Missions, Medical -- Gabon.; Organists.; Philosophers.; Theologians.; Gabon -- Description and travel.; Lambaréné (Moyen-Ogooué, Gabon); Correspondence.; Essays.; Lectures.; Notebooks.; Sermons.; Missionaries.; Musicians.; Physicians.; Theologians.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Purchased, in part, by Library Associates from Rhena Schweitzer Miller.
The bulk of the notebooks and the correspondence with both Hélène Schweitzer and Rhena Schweitzer were purchased from Rhena Schweitzer Miller with funds provided by Syracuse University Library Associates. Additional letters and notebooks, Albert Schweitzer's early papers, and the Nikos Kazantzakis manuscripts are the gift of Rhena Schweitzer Miller.
Copies of Schweitzer's letters to Rudolf Bultmann, an original letter to Hauptverband Baumwollindustrie Frankfurt, a map of Lambaréné, and an Erica Anderson portrait of Albert Schweitzer are the gift of Antje Bultmann Lemke.
A letter to Mrs. Otto A. Pokorny and an autograph portrait of Albert Schwietzer are the gift of Mrs. Carl H. Grathwol.
Letters to Irving Townsend, Columbia Records gift of Elizabeth Nestor, 2009.
The William P. Tolley Endowed Library Fund supported the purchase of concert program notes and a printed autograph portrait of Albert Schweitzer.
The mahogany box bearing Schweitzer's inscription is the gift of Kimberlee T. Knauf.
Inventory
- Correspondence/subject files
  - American Leprosy Mission, See Currier, Raymond P.
  - Anderson, Erica
    - Inventory of Erica Anderson correspondence (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1950-1965; 18 folders (Box 1)
      See also Writings: Scripts
  - Avey, Clarence F., 1946-1965 (Box 2)
  - Boegner, Alfred, July 9, 1905 (Box 2)
  - Bresslau, Harry, Dec. 22, 1911 (Box 2)
  - Bresslau, Hélène, See Schweitzer, Hélène
  - Bultmann, Antje, Oct. 11, 1931 (Box 2)
  - Bultmann, Rudolf, 1929; 1931 (Box 2)
  - Christian Medical Council for Overseas Work, See Hume, Edward
  - Columbia Records (Irving Townsend), 1952 (Box 2)
  - Courboin, Charles N., Dec. 28, 1946 (Box 2)
  - Currier, Raymond P., May 12, 1956 (Box 2)
  - Dahlberg, Edwin T., Apr. 23, 1945 (Box 2)
  - Eckert, Rhena, See Schweitzer, Rhena
  - Ehretsmann, Louisa, See Memorabilia: Correspondence by others
  - Schweitzer, Louisa (Box 2)
  - Evangelical Women's Union, See Pokorny, Mrs. Otto A.
  - Hagedorn, Hermann, 1944; n.d. (Box 2)
  - Hauptverband der Baumwollindustrie Frankfurt, June 28, 1955 (Box 2)
  - Heuss-Knapp, Elly, 1950 (Box 2)
  - Hill, Jerome, See Writings: Scripts
  - Hume, Edward, 1942-1944 (Box 2)
  - Kennedy, John F., 1962 (Box 2)
  - New South Wales Peace Committee, July 15, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Pokorny, Mrs. Otto A., June 11, 1933 (Box 2)
  - Riedert, J., Mar. 14, 1906 (Box 2)
  - Ross, Emory, 1941-1965; 17 folders (Box 2)
  - Schweitzer, Hélène
    - Selected list of correspondence (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1901-1906; 9 folders (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1907-1913; 9 folders (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1919-1939; 20 folders (Box 4)
  - Schweitzer, Louis, See Memorabilia: Correspondence by others
  - Schweitzer, Louisa, See Memorabilia: Correspondence by others
  - Schweitzer, Rhena
    - Selected list of correspondence (Box 5)
    - 1925-1965, 31 folders (Box 5)
  - Steinwascher, Rolf, 1959 (Box 5)
  - Urquhart, Clara, May 12, 1962 (Box 5)
  - Von Halen, Luise, See Memorabilia: Correspondence by others
  - Von Schubert, Margaret - recipient, See Memorabilia: Correspondence by others
  - Unidentified
    - "Dear Friend", June 10, 1908 (Box 5)
    - Re: request for medical supplies, 1963 (Box 5)
- Writings
  - Books
    - More from the Primeval Forest, working copy with notes for revision and photographs (Box 6)
  - Essays
    - "Friede oder Atomkrieg"
      - "Erster Appell: Verzicht auf Versuchsexplosionen"
        - Typescript, autograph (Box 6)
        - Holograph notes (Box 6)
        - Typescript, English translation (Box 6)
        - Typescript with notes, French translation (Box 6)
      - "Zweiter Appell: Die Gefahr eines Atomkrieges"
        - Typescript with notes, 4 copies, one bearing a signature (Box 6)
        - Typescript with notes, French translation (Box 6)
      - "Dritter Appell: Verhandlungen auf höchster Ebene"
        - Typescript with notes, 4 copies, one bearing a signature (Box 6)
        - Typescript with notes, French translation (Box 6)
    - "Für Japan" (Box 6)
    - "Für Reform des Orgelbaus", 1927 (Box 6)
    - "Die Geziehungen zwischen und farbigen Rassen" (Box 6)
    - "Jesus und wir", Jan. 23, 1906 (Box 7)
    - "Los von Unmenschlichkeit, los von Atomwaffen" (Box 7)
    - "Nachtrag zu 'Orgelbaukunst'", Feb. 1927 (Box 7)
    - "Paix ou Guerre Atomique", See "Friede oder Atomkrieg"
    - "Peace or Atomic War", See "Friede oder Atomkrieg"
    - "Von Neuen Testament" (Box 7)
  - Notebooks
    - [untitled], 1918-1919; names, addresses, schedules, notes for lectures (Box 7)
    - "Reise Herbst 1921 Reise Schweiz", diary of the Switzerland trip (Box 7)
    - "Reise nach Schweden Herbst 1921", diary of a concert and lecture tour through Sweden (Box 7)
    - [untitled], 1921; names, addresses, memory aids, timetables, income tax calculations (Box 7)
    - "Concert-r[?] Vortragsreise Schweden. Januar - April 1922 Reise Schweden-Berlin-Paris-England - Schweden", notes from the concert and lecture tour (Box 7)
    - "Reise England Früjahr 1922", notes on programs, organs and people during a concert tour of England (Box 7)
    - "Tournée in Dänemark Herbst 1922", notes about lectures, sermons, concerts and organs; remarks about people and accommodations; plans for a trip to Germany (Box 7)
    - [untitled], 1922; addresses; comments about people, organizations, and contributors (Box 7)
    - [untitled], 1922; addresses; comments about people in England, Ireland, Canada and the United States (Box 7)
    - "Reise nach Prag und München Januar 1923", notes from a concert tour to Prague (Box 7)
    - [untitled], 1923; addresses; notes on construction, medical problems, supplies needed for Africa; comments on book reviews (Box 7)
    - "Afrikareise Februar 1924", detailed description of the trip from Bordeaux to Africa; addresses; notes on medical issues (Box 7)
    - "Reise Schweden Herbst 27, Reise Dänemark Herbst 27 Rückkehr durch Deutschland Herbst 27", 1927; notes on a concert tour through Sweden and Denmark (Box 7)
    - "Reise Holland September 1927 Reise nach England September 1927", notes on a concert tour through the Netherlands and England (Box 7)
    - "Concerte Schweiz Herbst 1928", addresses; descriptions of programs and organs on a concert tour through Switzerland (Box 8)
    - "Concertreise Deutschland Herbst 1928", addresses; descriptions of programs and organs on a concert and lecture tour through Germany (Box 8)
    - "Reise Holland Früjahr 28, Reise England Früjahr 28, Rückkehr durch Holland Früjahr 28", 1928; descriptions of programs and organs; notes about people; addresses (Box 8)
    - "Notizbuch 1928", notes about lectures and concerts in the Netherlands and England; poems; hymns; addresses; royalty statements; notes on tropical diseases; a list of lectures given at the University of Strassburg from 1902 to 1912 (Box 8)
    - "Concert und Vortrage Reisen in Elsass und Deutschland 1929_Januar bis Juni", notes on programs, organs, people and accommodations; timetables; information about distribution of donations (Box 8)
    - "Voyage Strassbourg - Lambaréné Nov.-Dec. 1929", baggage list; addresses; expenses; notes during the voyage to Africa (Box 8)
    - "Notizbuch 1929", notes on daily events, incoming letters, and organs; poems; lists of books, clothing, medical supplies and potential personnel for Lambaréné; recipes; thoughts on the Apostle Paul (Box 8)
    - "Comm[andes] médicam[ents] Hôpital Schweitzer 1930-1951", orders for medicine, medical instruments, and books (Box 8)
    - "Notizbuch 1930", hospital accounts; supplies; names; addresses; comments about people who have applied to work at the hospital; clippings; quotes; jokes (Box 9)
    - "Therapeudische Notizen", 1930; medical notes (Box 9)
    - "Notizbuch 1931", notes on hospital business matters; clippings; quotes; abstracts of letters; notes on the history of the church in Günsbach; plans for future lecture tours (Box 9)
    - "1932 April Reise Holland Früjahr", notes on a concert and lecture tour through the Netherlands (Box 9)
    - "England Früjahr 1932", addresses; comments on people, concerts and lectures; notes on the conferring of an honorary doctorate at Oxford (Box 9)
    - "Paris - Berlin 1932 12 Nov.", addresses; appointments; notes about a meeting with Gerhard Hauptmann and Albert Einstein (Box 9)
    - "Vorträge und Konzerte 1932 Deutschland", lists of individuals and associations to be invited to concerts (Box 9)
    - "Notizbuch 1932", notes on salaries for doctors; travel notes from Germany, France, Switzerland, the Netherlands and Scotland; remarks on concerts and interviews; some family research; a list of expenditures; thoughts on the Goethe centennial; ideas on philosophy; plans for meetings with Ina Seidel, Widor, Einstein, Gerhard Hauptmann and Cosima Wagner (Box 9)
    - "Voyage à Paris 25_II_1933, 17 Avril 1934, 6_VII_1934", 1933-1934; notes, names and addresses from the concert tour to Paris. (The page following the entries for April 18 and 19, 1933 has a note written by Marcel Dupréon which Schweitzer has written "for Rhena Schweitzer - autograph of Marcel Dupré.") (Box 9)
    - "IVe Voyage à Lambaréné avec Brazza-Afrique 18 Marz - 22 April 1933", diary of the 4th Africa voyage, including expenses, events, and addresses for letters of thanks (Box 9)
    - "Listes des malades pour lesquelles il y a à établir une facture 1931", 1933; a list of patients who had been billed in 1931; notes on Chinese and Indian languages (Box 9)
    - "Notizbuch 1933", notes for the upcoming trip to Africa; remarks on books and lectures; quotes; poems; accounts; addresses with personal comments; list of birthdays of the Schweitzer family; a speech in Latin for Oxford University; technical notes on organs and medicine (Box 9)
    - "Voyage en Angleterre octobre 1934", addresses, schedule and notes from the concert tour to England and France (Box 9)
    - "Anfragen für Concerte Vorlesungen und Vorträge in England, zussamengestellt Reiseheften und Briefen - dazu Adressen", 1934; addresses from England, with inquiries about and invitations for concerts and lectures (Box 9)
    - [untitled], 1934; addresses; book and medical supply orders; notes on philosophy and language; memoranda about lectures, medical treatments, and a planned trip to England; newspaper clippings; poems; an abstract of a letter from Mendelssohn (Box 9)
    - "Vorträge in Schweiz Januar 1935", notes from a lecture tour through Switzerland, with themes, appointments, addresses, and a list of donations (Box 10)
    - "Départ pour Lambaréné. Docteur 5 février 1935", notes from the 5th voyage to Africa, with a baggage list (Box 10)
    - "Voyage en Angleterre - Herbst 1935 - Gifford - lectures II", plans for the trip to England; notes; addresses; technical information about organs; notes on concerts and lectures; clippings; quotes; poems; lists of purchases and orders; names of candidates for Lambaréné; a list of recordings; a review of the year 1936 (Box 10)
    - "Voage[sic] Lambaréné - Lausanne aôut-septembre 1935", notes from the 5th voyage to Africa, with a baggage list (Box 10)
    - Diary from the 5th voyage to Africa, and from the voyage to Europe, 1935; Addresses; comments about books; clippings; poems; notes on personnel matters; technical details about organs; thoughts on the philosophy of civilization; plans for future lecture tours (Box 10)
    - "Vorträge + Konzerte Schweiz April - Mai 1936", notes on programs, itinerary, and participating conductors and organizers; addresses; expenses of the concert and lecture tour through Switzerland (Box 10)
    - [untitled], 1936; notes on concerts and lectures; clippings; quotes; poems; lists of purchases and orders; names of candidates for Lambaréné; technical details about organs; a list of recordings; a review of the year 1936 (Box 10)
    - "Sur succession des ----- -----", 1937; notes on preparations for the 6th voyage to Africa; addresses; comments on correspondence; quotes; poems; thoughts about philosophy; a diary of the voyage (Box 10)
    - "Voyage sur --- Foucauld, Bordeaux-Port Gentil. Départ Afrique avec Foucauld (ancièn) 29_I_1937", notes made on the 6th voyage to Africa, including names of the crew and a detailed baggage list (Box 10)
    - "Uber werk bei --------", 1938; diary from Lambaréné, including medical issues, personnel matters, addresses; information about donations; plans for the upcoming trip to Europe; a review of the year 1938 (Box 10)
    - "2 voyages. Voyage de retour Lambaréné - Günsbach janvier 1939 sur Asie (11_1 - 2_2_39) et retour Lambaréné 14_2_39", notes on the two voyages; baggage list (Box 10)